Finding Aid for War of 1812 Collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- War of 1812 collection
  - 1812 September 22. [Henry Addington, Viscount] Sidmouth Partially Printed Document to Hopkins, Gray, & Glover; Whitehall, [London, England]., 1 page; "To all Commanders of His Majesty’s Ships of War and Privateers." Granting Hopkins, Gray, & Glover a license for their unarmed vessel to bring imported American grain to Cadiz. License issued according to the 1808 "Act to permit Goods secured in Warehouses in the Port of London to be removed to the Out Ports for Exportation to any Part of Europe…" Notes restrictions on French vessels and subjects. Ensures American cargoes and vessels will not be molested "on Account of any Hostilities that may exist between His Majesty and the said United States of America." No. 63 from Eyre and Strahan, His Majesty’s Printers.
  - 1812 September 25. J. Chandler AL to Daniel Chandler; Lexington., 2 pages; Refers to Hull’s surrender; "Hull's disgrace…fills the minds of people with sensations not easily described--the feds endeavour to excuse him…you mention your going to Montreal…God grant in going there you may go as conquerors not as conquered."
  - 1812 September 25. William Eustis LS to Joel Barlow; War Department., 2 pages; In code [directs Joel Barlow, an American agent abroad, to assist Henry Wilson. Wilson will secretly export arms to the United States from Ostend in Belgium].
  - 1812 September 26. Thomas Sewell DS; Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Offer of reward for information on the person who tried to destroy his gunpowder mills; "Several attempt have been made…this month to destroy my gunpowder mills near this…There being the stronges reason for believing that the agents in this affair- may be induced by prospects of reward- I do hereby bind myself to pay...fifteen hundred dollars, for such disclosures."
  - 1812 September 28. Henry Dearborn LS to Jacob Eustis; Head quarters, Greenbush., 1 page; Josiah Paine’s bill for payment due him by the U.S. government; "Mr. Payne of Portland was employed, at my request, to send an express to Passamaquoddy:--which service was performed with great dispatch.--His demand is 250…the charge is high - but it must be paid. - you will therefore please to discharge the demand."
  - 1812 September 30. John Parker Boyd ALS to Henry Dearborn; Eastern Division Head Quarters, Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Acknowledging advice; he encloses an earlier letter and an order to a major in the militia, "copies of which have been forwarded to the War Department."
  - 1812 October 3. John Widney ALS to Samuel Williams; Meadville, [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Has volunteered in Captain Harper's Company of Infantry. Mentions the election between Adamson Tannehill (1750-1820) and Captain Foster for General, bemoaning Tannehill's victory "…it is to be lamented that polliticks prevaild again[s]t Millatiry abillities." Uncertain if they will be sent to Buffalo or Cleveland. Notes his cousin William Irwin serving as a surgeon's mate. Acknowledges Samuel Williams's account of the "Escape of Captain Crush's Company." Discusses hard marches, daily camp life, and a violent attack against one of their camp sentries. See also John Widney ALS to Samuel Williams, May 13, 1813. [Original in Map Division, Small Maps 1813].
  - 1812 October 5. Ezra Canfield ALS to Mrs. Lucretia Canfield; [Batava]., 2 pages; Misses wife and family, refers to the potential American assault on Canada; "the contry is full of troops marching on the toe lines from all quarters it seems to be the opinion here that there will bee at least seventy thousands that will make an attack upon the Canadas within twenty days…"
  - 1812 October 5. John Schryack DS; Camp Urbana, [Ohio]., 2 pages; Receipt for $52 received from James Taylor, Quarter Master General, for amount owed to Diament Whitaker for the use of his corn field by "the Ohio Troops on their march Northward." Signed by R[eturn] J[onathan] Meigs (1764-1825), granting the Quarter Master General permission to pay the debt.
  - 1812 October 11. Thomas Bodley CyS., 1 page; Copy of an appointment of James Bradshaw to Forage Master; "He will proceed on the purchase forage for the regt. and will receive information of the route from Col. Campbell…"
  - 1812 October 14. John Reding, Jr. ADS; New Hampshire., 2 pages; Deposition regarding the capture of an American vessel, Abigail; "the sloop, having English Colours flying at the time, The Captain informed me he had a Protection against Capture by English Cruizers and Shew me a Licence from the British Government…" The crew believed that its load was English property and would be condemned if it entered the United States.
  - 1812 October 18. Ezra Canfield ALS to Mrs. Lucretia Canfield; Lewistown., 1 page; Description of a battle between his regiment and British troops. Also describes confusion after the battle; "the british want a sesation of arms and they are not willing to give up our oficers unless our regiment may be dischargd…"
  - 1812 October 27. Daniel D. Tompkins ALS to Peter Buell Porter; Buffalo, [New York]., 2 pages; Porter will be given medical supplies for the sick and wounded in hospitals at Lewiston and Black-Rock, obtain receipts from the surgeons for the supplies, and deliver the receipts back to Col. Livingston. Tompkins then dismisses him as Quartermaster General [of the New York State Militia].
  - 1812 October 29. Rebecca [Eustis] ALS to Abraham Eustis; Cambridge, [Massachusetts]., 3 pages; Upset by delays in the mail which have caused her letters to not reach Abraham before he marched for Plattsburg. Recently moved to Cambridge. Will not lie and say she is happy, but refuses to "tell you how miserable I am at intervals least it should clogg your military ardor." Hopeful for a cessation of hostilities, at least for the winter. "It seems as if heaven had really frowned upon our ill-fated country ever since the Declaration of this ill-managed war." Family news, everyone anxious about him. Addressed to Major Abraham Eustis, Plattsburg. See also D. S. Townsend ALS to Abr[aha]m Eustis, August 29, 1820, located in the Michigan Collection.
  - 1812 November 4. Thomas Buford LS to Thomas L. Butler; Lexington, [Kentucky]., 2 pages; Congratulates Butler on his appointment as deputy quartermaster general and mentions supplies forwarded for the troops at Vincennes; "You have been pleased to advise me to procure and forward supplies of Provisions for the Troops at Vincennes," including flour, whiskey, soap, and candles.
  - 1812 November 9. Broke, P[hilip] B[owes] Vere ALS to Dr. Hutchinson; Shannon, at sea., 4 pages; Harries the American Navy and expresses the need to humble the Americans; "The capture of poor Guerriere, tho by a very superior force will make the Yankees so insolent that perhaps they may force their ships to risque a battle - & they must be severely humbled before we can hope to make any peace with them, for their ignorance, conceit & rancour are at present beyond all bounds..."
  - 1812 November 14. James Winchester ALS to John H. Piatt; Camp Miami [Maumee, Ohio]., 1 page; Letter stressing the importance of obtaining supplies; "The necessity for accumulating supplies for the army at Fort Winchester increases…redouble your exertions to send on provisions - Salt - is indispensible to save our Beef that is falling every day - Liquor we have none of, on hand."
  - 1812 November 15. Amos Stoddard ALS to Lt. Bryson; Pittsburgh, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Regarding a paroled prisoner; "As I have found it impractiable to procure an experienced pilot at this place, to accompany a Public Boat to Cincinnati…I have availed myself of Lieutenant Darrah's offers of service on the occasion - and as he is a prisoner on parole, I have engaged, that he...be furnished with a public Horse to enable him to return over land."
  - 1812 November 17. Samuel Preston ALS to Miner and Butler; Rockport, [Pennsylvania]., 4 pages; Headlined "Thoughts on the President's Message Nov. 5th 1812." He lists 18 points, which includes criticism of Madison’s speech and comments on Hull’s failed invasion of Canada; "If J. Madison is reelected to select the members of the Military Tribunal, as the Prophet said to King Hezekiah, Gen'l Hull may set his house in order." Mentions matters pertaining to trade and politics.
  - 1812 November 28. Thomas Pickney ALS to Thomas A. Smith; Head Quarters, Charleston, [South Carolina]., 3 pages; Discusses the movement of regiments, specifically a Rifle Regiment and the 7th Regiment of Light Dragoons; includes another ALS, also from November 28, from Pickney to Smith on the subject.
  - 1812 November 28. James W. Bryson ALS to Robert Patterson; Newport, Kentucky., 1 page; Regarding the movement of troops and supplies.
  - 1812 December 7. John B. Campbell ALS to Robert Patterson; Camp at Dayton., 1 page; Request for horses to transport medical supplies, "not exceeding six with pack saddles, and lash ropes."
  - 1812 December 12. Nathaniel Leonard DS; Niagara River., 2 pages; Certificate of damage to Thomas Hustler’s house through its use as a military hospital; "his dwelling house in Lewiston having been taken and kept as an hospital by the troops in the service of the United States." Appraisers have been appointed to reach a dollar amount, which assessed the damages to $300. Includes Hustler's endorsement from March 31, [1813].
  - 1812 December 14. William H. Winder ALS to Henry Grindage; Black Rock, [New York]., 2 pages; Winter quarters; "We have abandoned all design of active operations for this season on this part of the line." They have been allowed to return to Baltimore for the winter and praises the conduct of the young soldiers.
  - 1812 December 15. Thomas Bodley ALS to Henry Brown; St. Marys., 2 pages; Encourages him to buy spare tonnage; "It is absolutely necessary that some person should purchase…Forage at Dayton…It is my wish you should Continue in the business." Requests money from Col. Patterson; "our boats have been frozen up & the troops in advancing are suffering..."
  - 1812 December 23. James Monroe ALS to Unknown; Washington, [D.C.]., 2 pages; Regarding the defense of Sackett’s Harbor, [New York]; mentioning American vessels built on Lake Ontario, "there is danger 'lest the enemy should…destroy them. This would be truly calamitous. I hope you have taken measures for their safety…"
  - 1812 December 29. John B. Campbell ADS., 1 page; Order to furnish the sick; "The Quarter Master at Dayton or his agent will furnish every thing necessary for the medical department so that the situation of those who have suffered in defence of our Country's rights and honour may be rendered as Comfortable as possible, for which the surgeons attending will make return."
  - 1812 - 1813. Receipts., 6 pages; Six receipts for such supplies as corn, flour, and the feeding of public horses.
  - 1812 ca.. Inhabitants of New Gloucester, Maine DS; New Gloucester, [Maine]., 3 pages; Measure, including 92 signatures, supporting active defense of the U.S. in the War of 1812; "we do hereby severally engage to consider ourselves, from this time, as ENROLLED AMONG THE DEFENDERS OF THIS COUNTRY, and that we will… hold ourselves in constant readiness to appear in the Field...when the call of our Government shall require our services."
  - 1812. Receipts., 9 pages; Receipts.
  - 1812-1813. Documents., 3 pages; Abstracts of purchases for the army.
  - [1812 ca.]. Connecticut Volunteers AD; [Fairfield, Connecticut]., 4 pages; Proposed rules and regulations for the formation of a Volunteer Company of Musketry; "As soon as thirty or more men of the town of Fairfield shall have subscribed to this paper, on notice being given They shall assemble at some convenient place for the purpose of organising a volunteer comp. to serve during the war..."
  - [1812]. Benjamin Harrison DS., 1 page; Inventory of articles belonging to a deceased ensign, his brother Joseph Harrison.
  - [ca. 1812]. United States DS to The Wyandots of Solomons Town, [Ohio]; Quarter Master’s Department, North-Western Army., 2 pages; Money owed for beaver killed by General Tupper; "four Beever killed & made use of by General Tuppers detachments of Ohio Militia & estimated to weigh 1200 pounds by General Tupper..$48.00." Signed by William Henry Harrison.
  - 1813 January 19. A. A. Albert Gallatin ALS to Thomas Newton; Treasury Department [Washington, D.C.]., 1 page; Concerning the need to rebuild a lighthouse; "I have the honor to enclose the copy of a letter just received from the Collector of Wilmington N.Ca. under the circumstances stated by him; no other remedy appears efficient than the rebuilding of the light house in a safer place; and this cannot be done without a legislative sanction."
  - 1813 January 25. John Cotton Smith Pr. DS to Elisha Hinsdale; Hartford, [Connecticut]., 1 page; Appointment to Lieutenant of the Torrington Company of Volunteers.
  - 1813 February 1. Samuel Gaxton ALS to Calvin Stebbins; Attica, [New York]., 3 pages; Events in Canada since start of war; his experiences in camp has led him to "a full knowledge of the Conduct, of the great men of our Nations; or in other words the Men in Power; and suffer me to tell you that in my opinion they are leading us all to ruin." He mentions Hull's defeat and the "attempt of Smith to invade Canada; all fruitless..."
  - 1813 February 10 and 1813 May 3. B.F. Stickney ALS, ADS to Jacob Fowler; McPherson’s Block House., 12 pages; Letter and warrant for Captain Lewis, a Shawnee Chief; "you have taken a retain a horse belonging to Capt Lewis. The horse was delivered to Lewis by order of Gen Harrison... as will appear by a certificate Lewis now holds." Includes a receipt for a horse pressed into public service dated May 3, 1813 for $60.
  - 1813 February 11. John Armstrong DS; Department of War, [Washington, D.C.]., 1 page; Order regarding payment of troops; "The paymaster is required to cause to be advanced to the officers non-commisioned officers and privates of two Regiments of militia, which have been called into service by Gov. Meigs in the State of Ohiol Two months pay and amoluments."
  - 1813 February 25. Charles Wale Partially printed DS; Fort Royal, Martinique., 2 pages; License for safe passage for any unarmed American ship from New London (Conn.) to Fort Royal. Signed by Wale, the British Governor of Martinique. Tonnage endorsed on page two, for the Brig Godfry & Mary, New London, May 17, 1813.
  - 1813 February 20. George Beale ADS to William Jones; Plattsburg, [New York]., 2 pages; Regarding payment for provisions and "the payment of the officers and men on this station."
  - 1813 February 20. Ohio Legislature Document; Groton., 1 page; Regarding the Lake Erie Tax for 1812; "A Tax Bill for the Proprieters in the 1st. Section in the Town of Groton in the County of huron, in the State of Ohio, in that part called firelands, and was Levyed by the Legislator…in, and for, the year 1812, which Tax is $28..78.- and each proprietors is as followeth."
  - 1813 February 22. John Clopton ALS; Representative Chamber [Washington, D.C.]., 1 page; Clopton, a U.S. Representative from Virginia, nominates George Kennon to be navy surgeon; "I have been requested to nominate Doctor George T. Kennon for the appointment of a surgeon in the navy. Though not personally acquainted with Doctor Kennon, such recommendations of him has been communicated to me that, I cannot hesitate in nominating him to you."
  - 1813 February 23. W[illiam] Jones ALS to Manuel Eyre; Washington, [D.C.]., 2 pages; Regarding the non-importation act; "Nothing could justify the measure but the conviction that it is or soon will be a mere nominal Act defeated by evasion and smuggling…"
  - 1813 March 15. J. Broadus DS to Frederick Spofford; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Certificate of resignation as an ensign in the Massachusetts militia; he is honorably discharged.
  - 1813 March 18. Joseph Lee Smith ALS to Joseph Kinney; Burlington, [Vermont]., 1 page; Informing Kinney that he and ensign Brower are indispensable to the regiment going to Sackett’s Harbor, and to "keep your destination a secret."
  - 1813 March 28. N. Sherwood ALS to Ezra Lewis., 3 pages; He has been drafted, but his brother has gone in his place; "Harrison our Noble Commander has at that place between Six and Seven Thousand Kentucky that Noble and Patriotic Stat, are Raising three Thousand Vollen Teers and their Governor is to Command in Person."
  - 1813 April 5. E. I. DuPont ALS to John Hancock; Wilmington., 1 page; Concerning delayed shipments of gunpowder; "They would be exposed to Capture by Sea & There is not yet any line of waggons running between NYork & Boston…"
  - 1813 April 25. H[erbert] Sawyer ALS to John Wilson Croker; Bath., 11 pages; Report on activities of the U.S. fleet off the American coast on the outbreak of the War of 1812.
  - 1813 April 28. Return Jonathan Meigs ALS to Col. Enos; Franklinton, [Ohio]., 1 page; Orders for men to search countryside for Native Americans; "Understanding that the frontiers of your Regiment are apprehensive of Danger from the Indians…you are authorized to detach from your Regiment - One Company - to scour the Country on your frontier in that Direction..."
  - 1813 May 1. Sir John Borlase Warren ALS to George Cockburn; H.M.S. San Domingo off Swamp Point., 3 pages; Regarding operations along the Chesapeake shore; discusses a prisoner exchange, mentions Baltimore and Annapolis. (Box 3)
  - 1813 May 1. Simon Larned ALS to Charles Larned; Cantonment Greenbush, [New York]., 3 pages; Regarding family news and troop movements; "The troops from all Quarters are moving to Buffaloe [sic] & Sackets Harbour…I think however we shall soon have permanent foothold on Canada side of the Lake. The Recruiting service the last winter has been very successfull."
  - 1813 May 9. [Manuel Eyre] ADf to [William Jones]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 6 pages; Concerns the defense of Philadelphia; approximately $30,000 funds will be appropriated for this purpose. Includes a partial list of resolutions pertaining to the defense.
  - 1813 May 9 and 1813 May 10. Jacob Baker ALS to Isaac Launch; Fort Nelson [near Portsmouth, Virginia]., 3 pages; Description of Norfolk and Fort Nelson; "I had hoped to find Norfolk a neat and tolerable well built city but I believe I am to be disapointed in every town on this side of the ridge." Describes the building and the effect of the tide; "we are about a mile below Portsmouth in the rear of Fort Nelson a strong and most excellent fortification."
  - 1813 May 12. W[illiam] Jones ALS to Manuel Eyre; Washington, [D.C.]., 6 pages; Private correspondence concerning the defense of Philadelphia.
  - 1813 May 13. John Widney ALS to Samuel Williams; Concord, [Pennsylvania?]., 3 pages; Enclosing a map of Black Rock and Presque Isle on Erie [present]. Hopes William will send a map in return. Provides news of the American forces on the Niagara frontier, including the capture of York, the death of General Pike, and many deaths to a mine accident. Mentions Native Americans taken prisoner and Commodore Chauncey capturing British ships and taking possession of the lake. Includes two pen and ink maps, one of Black Rock, New York, and the other of Erie, Pennsylvania, noting military camps and positions, details of the Canadian shore, and Fort Erie. [Original in Map Division Small Maps]
  - 1813 May 17. [Manuel Eyre] ADf to [William Jones]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Regarding the defense of Philadelphia.
  - 1813 May 19. Pearl Spofford ALS to Frederick Spofford; Portland, [Maine]., 2 pages; Discusses the risks and rewards of trade during wartime; "no more goods can be had without giving an enormous price."
  - 1813 May 25. Morris Smith Miller ALS to [William Meredith]; Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Forwarding letters and best wishes.
  - 1813 May 26. John Christian, Jr. ALS to Jacob Van Lear; Augusta County, [Virginia]., 3 pages; Selecting a captain; Major Henderson has resigned and Captain Abney has assumed Henderson's former post, and thus they will be left without a captain "and it is no known what will be done with us…there is also a report that General Harrison has had a battle with the Indians and has killed and taken a great number of them..."
  - [1813 June 3, delivered]. Manuscript speech., 10 pages; Critical speech against the war with England, "Read at Petersham before Washington Benevolent Society of Barre". The writer questions the motives and justifications for war.
  - 1813 June 4. E. L. Shittock ALS to General Woolsey; Sackett’s Harbor, [New York]., 2 pages; Pleas for supplies and updates on recent war events; "we have been anxiously expecting their arrival long before this…Our men are quite naked & extreemly in want of Clothing…due for Godsake forward them on with all possible expedition, on the most direct road--if it should not be possible to send all on at once..."
  - 1813 June 5. State Garrison of Lt. Col. Warburton DS; Amherstburg, [Ontario]., 1 page; Details of number of troops, officers, and stations for Warburton’s garrison.
  - 1813 June 8. Thomas Gholson ALS to Robert Brint [Brent]., 1 page; Regarding two claims for deceased soldiers; "It is possible the returns from the pay master may cover these two cases. Will you do me the particular favor to address to me a few lines on the situation of these claims?"
  - 1813 June 12. Pearl Spofford ALS to Frederick Spofford; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Concerning the defense of Deer Island and rumor of fleet on Lake Erie.
  - 1813 June 18. Sir Francis Freeling LS to C. Saverland, Sr.; London, [England]., 2 pages; Remuneration offered to captains for losses sustained by vessels commanded by Captain Bell and Captain Rogers during missions on the American coast; Bell has been awarded £350 and Rogers £300.
  - 1813 July 6. William Abney ALS to Jacob Vanlear; Augusta County, [Virginia]., 2 pages; Responds to Vanlear's news of false alarms in army camps; "that is what takes place frequently in an army sometimes through desighn in order to try the men that they may be better acquainted how to manage in case the alarm at any time should move to be true."
  - 1813 July 6. Samuel P. Fitch ALS to Theophilus W. Fitch; New London, [Connecticut]., 3 pages; Discusses Stephen Decatur’s squadron being chased into New London harbor by British, an engagement to repel British, and submarine warfare.
  - 1813 July 10. Morris Smith Miller ALS to William Meredith; Washington, [D.C.]., 3 pages; Representative Miller of New York discusses taxes; "You will have observed the course which our friends have adopted in regard to the taxes: the balance of opinion…that the Taxes did not afford a fair opportunity for [canvassing] the great question of peace or war. -It is expected that the President willl answer Webster on Monday..."
  - 1813 July 11. William Graves ALS; Watertown, [New York?]., 2 pages; Sending Mr. Smith to "Enquire of some Engraver what the Expense of Engraving a Map would be." Has produced a 2 foot x 3.5 foot map of "the province of Upper Canada and the present Seat of War" and describes the content, including counties, waterways, military sites, and the state of land surveys. Map also covers "the Northern Frontier of the state of New York North Frontier of Ohio on Lake Erie Michigan Territory." Believes the map would sell well, "as a great Number of people are desirous to see the Countrey that the American Army are Contending for." Signed, "William Graves late Kings Surveyor of Upper Canada."
  - 1813 July 11. Ninian Pinkney ALS to Henry Dearborn; Niagara., 3 pages; Pinkney’s suggestions about Dearborn’s camp have been put in place, such as "removing the prisoners from the Hospitals as fast as they recovered, removing the Sick & wounded of our army, drawing in Troops from the Town to Camp…"